Finding Aid for Dorwin Cartwright Papers 1943-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dorwin Cartwright Papers 1943-1979
Cartwright, Dorwin
1 linear foot and 1 oversize folder.
Founder and director of the Research Center for Group Dynamics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, an organization that later merged with the Survey Research Center of the University of Michigan to form the Institute for Social Research. Correspondence, reports, memoranda, articles, lectures, and an unfinished manuscript pertaining to research on war bond sales for the U. S. Bureau of Agricultural Economics, 1943-1946; also papers on subsequent research on social behavior and psychology conducted at the University of Michigan.
85110 Aa 2; UAl
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Cartwright (donor no. 7071 )
The collection is open for research.
Dorwin Philip Cartwright was born March 3, 1915 in Des Moines, Iowa. He received his BA from Swarthmore College in 1937, his MA in 1938 and PhD in 1940, both from Harvard. After serving briefly as a research fellow at the University of Iowa, he joined the staff of U.S. Department of Agriculture's Bureau of Agricultural Economics. As director of the Division of Program Surveys, Cartwright conducted research on war bond sales and public attitudes toward bond drives with his colleague, Rensis Likert. (See Rensis Likert collection for related material)
At the conclusion of World War II in 1945, Cartwright became an associate professor and in 1947 director of the Research Center for Group Dynamics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Under his directorship the Center became a leading sponsor of social science data research. The following year he was persuaded by his former colleague, Rensis Likert, to move the Center to the Survey Research Center at the University of Michigan. The two centers later merged to form the Institute of Social Research (ISR).
At Michigan, while continuing to head the Research Center for Group Dynamics, Cartwright became an associate professor of psychology and authored numerous articles on social attitudes and the quantification of group behavior. He later became research coordinator at ISR and served on the board of directors for the Social Science Research Council.
The Dorwin Cartwright Papers reflect Cartwright's career as researcher of war bond sales for the Bureau of Agricultural Economics during World War II and his later activities as professor and staff member of the Institute of Social Research. The papers contain some correspondence reflecting his transfer from Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) to the University of Michigan, but include primarily reprints of Cartwright's articles and reports while on the staff at the University. The papers also contain some of Cartwright's lectures and an unpublished manuscript in which he summarized his research on war bond sales. Accompanying the war bond materials are several promotional advertising posters from World War II.
Subjects:
Cartwright, Dorwin.; Social surveys--Research.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Bureau of Agricultural Economics, 1943-1950
  - Memoranda, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Summary Reports, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Survey Questionnaires, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - War Bond Promotional Material, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    See also oversize folder, UAl
  - Unfinished Manuscript and Related Correspondence re: War Bond Research, 1946-1950 (Box 1)
- Research Center for Group Dynamics
  - Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 1)
  - Reports and Memoranda, 1946-1950 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, 1949-1978 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Reprinted Articles (unbound), 1948-1979 (Box 1)
  - Bound Articles
    - 1945-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1)